Gabriel Lima

gabriel.lima@kaist.ac.kr·+82-10-7280-7236 https://thegcamilo.github.io/·@gcamilo_lima

Data Science Group, Institute for Basic Science, 55 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon, South Korea, 34126

Last Updated: November, 2021

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am a computer scientist interested in understanding people's perception of artificial intelligence (AI) systems and how they will morally and legally affect society. I address these research questions through the lens of moral and legal responsibility, and I investigate the possible conflicts between the regulation and development of machines and the public view of these new technologies. My research aims to study how people perceive the moral agency and patiency of AI systems to embed their opinion on normative research and policymaking.

EDUCATION

Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST)

Daejeon, South Korea, Mar. 2021 - Present

M.S. in Computer Science. Advisor: Meeyoung Cha.

Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST)

Daejeon, South Korea, Feb. 2017 - Feb. 2021

Advanced B.S. in Computer Science (with honors).

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland, Sep. 2019 - Feb. 2020

Exchange Semester at the School of Computer and Communication Sciences.

CONFERENCE PAPERS

Gabriel Lima, Jiyoung Han, Meeyoung Cha. "Others Are to Blame: A Multi-Faceted View on Whom People Consider Responsible For Online Misinformation." *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)*. 2022.

Gabriel Lima, Nina Grgić-Hlača, Meeyoung Cha. "Human Perceptions on Moral Responsibility of AI: A Case Study in AI-Assisted Bail Decision-Making." *Proceedings of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. 2021.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445260

Gabriel Lima, Changyeon Kim, Seungho Ryu, Chihyung Jeon, Meeyoung Cha. "Collecting the Public Perception of Al and Robot Rights." *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)*. 2020.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3415206

Gabriel Lima, Chihyung Jeon, Meeyoung Cha, Kyungsin Park. "Will Punishing Robots Become Imperative in the Future?" Extended Abstracts of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 2020. https://doi.org/10.1145/3334480.3383006

Gabriel Lima, Sungkyu Park, Meeyoung Cha. "Robots for Class President: Children's Positions Toward AI Robot Rights." *Proceedings of the Korea Computer Congress (KCC)*. 2019.

Gabriel Lima, Jin Yeong Bak. "Speech Emotion Classification using Raw Audio Input and Transcriptions." *Proceedings of the* 2018 *International Conference on Signal Processing and Machine Learning*. 2018. https://doi.org/10.1145/3297067.3297089

JOURNAL PAPERS

Gabriel Lima, Meeyoung Cha, Chihyung Jeon, Kyung Sin Park. "The Conflict Between People's Urge to Punish AI and Legal Systems." *Frontiers in Robotics and AI*. 2021.

Gabriel Lima, Meeyoung Cha, Chihyung Jeon, Kyung Sin Park. "On the Social-Relational Moral Standing of Al: An Empirical Study Using Al-Generated Art." *Frontiers in Robotics and Al*. 2021. https://doi.org/10.3389/frobt.2021.719944

Gabriel Lima, Meeyoung Cha, Chiyoung Cha, Hyeyoung Hwang. "COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance in the US and UK in the Early Phase of the Pandemic: Al-Generated Vaccines Hesitancy for Minors, and the Role of Governments." *Journal of the Korean Data Analysis Society*. 2021.

http://doi.org/10.37727/jkdas.2021.23.3.1043

Meeyoung Cha, Chiyoung Cha, Karandeep Singh, **Gabriel Lima**, Yong-Yeol Ahn, Juhi Kulshrestha, Onur Varol. "Prevalence of Misinformation and Factchecks on the COVID-19 Pandemic in 35 Countries: Observational Infodemiology Study." *JMIR Human Factors*. 2021.

https://doi.org/10.2196/23279

WORKSHOP PAPERS

Gabriel Lima, Meeyoung Cha. "Descriptive AI Ethics: Collecting and Understanding the Public Opinion." Ethics in Design Workshop at the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW). 2020.

https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.05957

Gabriel Lima, Meeyoung Cha. "Responsible AI and Its Stakeholders." Fair and Responsible AI Workshop at 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 2020.

https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.11434

WORK EXPERIENCES

School of Humanities & Social Sciences, KAIST

Daejeon, South Korea, Aug. 2021 - Present

Teaching Assistant of the Scientific Writing class (CC500). Responsible for grading students' research papers and assisting with administrative tasks.

School of Computing, KAIST

Daejeon, South Korea, Aug. 2021 - Dec. 2021

Teaching Assistant of the Data Science Methodology class (CS564). Responsible for preparing and grading class assignments and assisting with administrative tasks.

HONORS AND AWARDS

KAIST School of Humanities and Social Sciences Best Paper Award

Spring Semester, 2020

Received for the paper titled "How Granting Rights to AI and Robots Might Conflict with Human Rights."

KAIST School of Computing Dean's List

Fall Semester, 2018

Received for outstanding academic achievement.

Best Presentation Award

Nov. 2018

Received at the International Conference on Signal Processing and Machine Learning 2018.

KAIST Graduate/Undergraduate Research Project (GURP) GURP Funding

Jan. 2018

Received KRW 8,000,000 (USD 6,700) for a research project on classifying emotion from raw speech data.

ACADEMIC SERVICES

Reviewer

We Robot Conference 2021

Conference for Truth and Trust Online 2021

Oct. 2021

Invited to present my research on people's attribution of responsibility for online misinformation (published at ACM CSCW, 2022).

Max Planck Institute for Research on Collective Goods

Apr. 2021

Invited to present my research on people's perception of legal personhood for AI and robots (published at Frontiers in AI and Robotics, 2021).

Conference for Truth and Trust Online 2020

Oct. 2020

Invited to present my research on the COVID-19 infodemic and its association with vaccine hesitancy (under review).

IT and Law Conference 2020

Aug. 2020

Invited to present my research on people's perception of legal personhood for AI and robots (published at Frontiers in AI and Robotics, 2021).

Nokia Bell Labs Students' Day

Nov. 2019

Invited to present my research on people's perception of legal personhood for AI and robots (published at Frontiers in AI and Robotics, 2021).

REFERENCES

Prof. Meeyoung Cha, mcha@ibs.re.kr

Chief Investigator of the Data Science Group at the Institute for Basic Science (IBS) and Associate Professor at the KAIST School of Computing.

Prof. Jiyoung Han, jiyoung.han@kaist.ac.kr

Assistant Professor at the KAIST Moon Soul Graduate School of Future Strategy.

Dr. Karandeep Singh, karandeepbrar@gmail.com

Senior Researcher at Data Science Group in the Institute for Basic Science (IBS).

Nina Grgić-Hlača, nghlaca@mpi-sws.org

PhD Candidate at the Max Planck Institute for Software Systems (MPI-SWS) and the Max Planck Institute for Research on Collective Goods.